<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The splendour of the spouse A sermon preached in the parish church of Ware, Anno Domini, 1638. By Augustine Hill, rector of Dengey, in the county of Essex.</title>
            <author>Hill, Augustine, d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13468</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116585</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851801</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851801</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17093</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03347)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17093)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1311:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The splendour of the spouse A sermon preached in the parish church of Ware, Anno Domini, 1638. By Augustine Hill, rector of Dengey, in the county of Essex.</title>
                  <author>Hill, Augustine, d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. P[urslowe] for Nicholas Bourne, and are to be sold at his shop, at the south entrance of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17093:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17093:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SPLENDOVR OF THE SPOUSE A SERMON Preached in the Pariſh Church of WARE, <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 1638.</p>
            <p>BY AUGUSTINE HILL, Rector of <hi>Dengey,</hi> in the County of ESSEX.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>BERN.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Paſcimur &amp; patimur.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>AUG.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Vſque ad hujus ſeculi ſinem inter perſecutiones mundi, &amp; conſolationes Dei procurrit Eccleſia.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by E. P. for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the South Entrance of the Royall Exchange. 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17093:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17093:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE SIR THOMAS FANSHAW Knight of the Bath, his Majeſties Remembrancer in the Court of Exchequer.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the greateſt happineſse that ever did befall me, that I was aſsumed into your noble Family where I was fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed once, and a ſecond time likewiſe with Eccleſiaſticall promotions, without any deſerts, yea little or none attendance. A true Friend is decyphered to be an Angell clothed with fleſh and blood, ſuch have you beene to me, the moſt carefull and faithfull friend that ever poore Scholler had. Comming to pay my annuall tribute of thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſse, a Sermon, it pleaſed you to accept of it, and to caſt a reſpective eye more then ordinary towards me for it, though there be nothing in it to be affected, and in my ſelfe no affectation at all of it, but rather an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt mine owne imbecillity and endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that I was not able to ſpeake of thoſe heavenly
<pb facs="tcp:17093:3"/> things in that manner as might raiſe my hearers to divine cogitations. What weight there is in it comes from your ballance and favourable conſtruction, for it was handled in plaine familiar words, rather to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe clearely the matter, then to hunt for poliſhed phraſes, and my deſire is more to ſpeake <hi>fortia quam diſerta,</hi> as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith, things of ſtrength then eloquence, and rather <hi>vivere</hi> then <hi>loqui,</hi> as <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutius Felix</hi> obſerves, to live, then ſpeake them.</p>
            <p>But I am a man compaſſed with infirmity, 'tis truly ſaid of me, my bodily preſence is weake, and my ſpeech contemptible, <hi>2 Corin. 10.10.</hi> But ſuch was your ſweet diſpoſition that you ſtill caſt a mantle upon mine infirme carriage, which hath engaged my heart in a more thankefull obſervance towards your worthy ſelfe. In teſtimony whereof I preſent to you this poore Sermon as a publique Record, that to your Noble Family I owe myſelfe, and from thence have received all the lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and meanes of ſubſiſtence which I now enjoy, my loynes and bowels bleſſe you continually. The Lord encreaſe upon you the bleſſings of heaven above, the bleſſings of the deepe that lyeth under, the bleſſings of the breaſts and of the wombe, <hi>Gen. 49.25.</hi> and the goodwill of him that dwelt in the buſh dwell with you for ever, are the prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours moſt thankefully and humbly devoted, AUG. HILL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17093:3"/>
            <head>THE SPLENDOUR OF THE SPOVSE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>CANT. 2.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>As the Lily among Thornes, ſo is my Love among the Daughters.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have gleaned at this time in <hi>Solomons</hi> Field, and that parcell of his called the Canticles, a Song of Songs, by way of eminency; for though there be many other ſacred Songs, as that of <hi>Moſes,</hi> of <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 15. Iudges 5.</note> and of the ſweet Singer of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Solomons</hi> owne Songs were a thouſand and five, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.32. yet this not onely exceeds all them, but all other mentioned in holy writ.<note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Hall.</hi>
               </note> Let me uſe the words of a truly Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine man. Who can read this Booke with underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and not be tranſported from the world, from himſelfe, and be any where ſave in heaven before his time? there is nothing in it but ſavours of ſpirituall exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and ſoule raviſhment; If I ſay no more of it, it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient that it is <hi>Solomons,</hi> a man above a man, above him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who being raviſhed in ſpirit, and taken up as it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17093:4"/> were into the third heavens, warbled out that ſweet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity and neareneſſe, that is, and ſhall be betwixt Chriſt and his Church,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.32.</note> that great myſterie as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calls it. Interpreters are at oddes about the former verſe, but agree in this, that it is the voyce of Chriſt concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Church, either deſcribing her preſent condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongſt others, or preferring her before them, or perſwading her how ſhee ought to demeane her ſelfe amongſt them, to retaine her native beauty and ſweetneſſe, though ſhee be beſet with never ſo many thornes.</p>
            <p>There is in the Text ſomething poſitive, ſomething comparative, the poſitive part is, that the Church is Chriſt his Love, the other are Daughters, the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative part takes up the reſt of the words.</p>
            <p>The poſitive part ſhewes the ſweet ſtile and title which Chriſt gives to his Church; He calls Her Love, and with a happy appropriation, my Love, which is a terme both of propriety and poſſeſſion. Others which are not the Church are called by the name of Daughters, by which are meant either Forraine Congregations, or ſuch as live within the pale of the viſible Church, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long not to him, therefore he forbeares to challenge his intereſt in them, and leaves them, to a common appellation, the Daughters, not my Daughters.</p>
            <p>The comparative part hath theſe things obvious to every eye: Firſt the ſubjects of this reſemblance, the Church is like the Lilly, the others are like Thornes. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the ſcituation of the reſembled parties. The Church is like the Lilly among the Thornes.</p>
            <p>The ſtile which Chriſt gives his Church is Love. It comes neareſt his owne nature, for God is love, it beſt reſembleth his benefits done for her,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 4.16. Epheſ. 5.25.</note> husbands love your wives as Chriſt loved his Church, and how he loved it he expreſſeth in a way beyond humane expreſſion, he gave himſelfe for it, he loved it better then he loved
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17093:4"/> himſelfe. <hi>Dilexiſtime magis quam te, quando mori voluiſti pro me. Auguſt.</hi> And it beſt ſets forth the reference ſhe hath to him, as being his Spouſe, his Bride. The ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant muſt honour his maſter, the Diſciple muſt attend for inſtruction, the wife muſt love her husband,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>amor ab amando, non honorando,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> and he gives theſe reaſons for it, <hi>una utriuſque haereditas, una domus, una menſa, unus etiam thorus,</hi> and there is no fitter a union of theſe then love.</p>
            <p>The originall then of the Churches bliſſe is Chriſt his love towards her. The firſt ſpring of election is love.<note place="margin">Rom. 9. Iohn 3.16. Hoſeah 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>Jacob</hi> have I loved, the maine Conduit or Ciſterne of Redemption is love. God ſo loved the world, the ſtreams of vocation and ſanctification. I drew thee with the cords of a man, with the bands of love, and the maine Ocean of eternall glory, <hi>In amore haec inſunt omnia,</hi> all is from love. There neither is nor can be any in her to move him to love her, much leſſe to deſerve his love, not her beauty, ſhe acknowledgeth her ſelfe black, no <hi>Miriam</hi> more leprous,<note place="margin">Can. 1.</note> no polluted <hi>Thamar</hi> more ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the eyes of an <hi>Amnon</hi> then ſhe in his eyes, when he firſt tooke liking to her, not her parentage, for her father was an <hi>Amorite,</hi> her mother a <hi>Hittite,</hi> nor her portion, for what was hers naturally,<note place="margin">Ezekiel 16.</note> but ſinne and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting death the wages of it? nor her parts, for the beſt child of grace acknowledgeth, In me there dwelleth no manner of thing that is good; all then was in him free and pure love. Now we ſay <hi>magnes amoris amor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7</note> love hath an attractive power to draw love, therefore let every Spouſe of Chriſt remember to returne love to him againe, that every heart may plead for it ſelfe, as <hi>Peter</hi> did, <hi>Lord thou knoweſt that I love thee.</hi> O then let us pitch and ſettle our affections upon him, who is as Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſaith, <hi>verè amans &amp; amabilis,</hi> one moſt truly loving us, and moſt worthy to be beloved of us: the Apoſtle pronounceth an extreame <hi>Anathema</hi> to him that failes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17093:5"/> in the retribution of it. If any man love not the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 16.22.</note> let him be <hi>Anathema Maranatha,</hi> and it ſhould be a double engagement of our obedience and thanke: and let us not onely with the inward man love him; but with the outward alſo honour and confeſſe him, who pleads for us before his Father in heaven: 'tis but a dead heart that hath a dumbe voyce when Chriſt his cauſe is in queſtion: <hi>Canes latrare poſſunt pro Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, &amp; non vis me latrare pro Chriſto?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hier. Tract. <hi>3.</hi> op. <hi>40.</hi>
               </note> ſaith Saint <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> to <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> the Dogges will barke for their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and wilt thou not have me ſpeake for Chriſt? and he goes on: <hi>ſi iſta cauſadi ſcordiae est, mori poſſum, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere non poſſum:</hi> if that be the cauſe of our jarres, I may dye before hold my peace, yea let us ſo farre as in us lyeth, not ſuffer him to be blaſphemed by others: it was the zealous reſolution of that holy Father. <hi>Ego ſi pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem, ſi matrem, ſi uxorem, ſi filios, ſi germanos adverſum Chriſtum meum audiviſſem iſta dicentes, quaſi rabidus canis blaſphemantia ora laceraſſem, &amp; fuiſſet in primis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus mea ſuper eos:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id, op. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> And laſtly it ſhould be a double en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement of our obedience and thankefulneſſe of our obedience to live unto him who hath ſo dearely loved us, as to dye for us, and our thankefulneſſe may have that heavenly burden of the Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5, 6. To him that hath loved us and waſhed us from our ſinnes in his owne blood, and hath made us Kings and Prieſts unto God and his Father, to him be glory and dominion for ever and ever, Amen.</p>
            <p>The word is rendred <hi>Vicina,</hi> my neighbour, adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Inhabitant. <hi>Themistocles</hi> having a houſe to ſell, commended it, that it had <hi>bonum vicinum,</hi> a good neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; the Churches bliſſe is, that Chriſt is pleaſed to dwell with them, yea in them, and make a reſolution as in the <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Here will I dwell, for I have a delight therein:</hi> and not onely <hi>vicina,</hi> but <hi>proxima,</hi> my neareſt one, both for counſell and comfort, he revealeth his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17093:5"/> to them, and is ready at all aſſayes to helpe them, yea <hi>amica</hi> my friend, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was called the friend of God, <hi>Jac.</hi> 2.23. He need feare no enemy who hath God to his friend: yet the originall word goes further, for it is taken from feeding or converſing together, and expreſſeth that inward familiarity and union that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them. It muſt teach us all, by no meanes to eſtrange our ſelves from Chriſt, but to keepe a correſpondence with him, to cheriſh our familiarity, friendſhip, to preſerve our union, that we profeſſing him to be ours, he may confeſſe us to be his, as he doth his Church here, My love, which is a terme both of propriety, and of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion. Of propriety, he claimes a ſpeciall intereſt in his Church, and he hath a true right in us all, both by making us his at the firſt, and by buying us againe, when we had made away our ſelves: his deare purchaſe we are, therefore let us not alienate our ſelves from him, either in our affection, for he is the proper and adaequate object of our love, <hi>minus east è te amat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>qui ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid praeter te amat, quod non propter te amat,</hi> he loves thee amiſſe who loves any thing beſides thee, which he loves not in and for thee; nor in our obedience, but wholly devote our ſelves to him, and him alone, that none may have the honour of our ſervice but he, that abaſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to ſave us. Of poſſeſſion: he hath a ſpeciall care and cuſtody of his Church, he keepes them as choycely as his jewels, as the apple of his owne eye, he keepes their head as with a ſhield, that not a haire of it ſhall periſh: yea their very feet, that they daſh them not againſt a ſtone.</p>
            <p>By the Daughters are meant either forraigne Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, as the Daughter of Babylon,<note place="margin">Pſalme 137.</note> or elſe (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) ſuch as live within the Pale of the viſible Church, enjoy the ſame holy Word and Sacraments, which the elect Spouſe of Chriſt doth, yet are they Thornes to his Lily: <hi>Spinae propter malignitatem morum, filiae propter Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentorum
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17093:6"/> communionem:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Vincentio Epiſt. <hi>48.</hi> Id, in Pſ. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>eadem profeſſio, ſed non idem cor,</hi> ſaith the ſame Father, they have the ſame profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but not the ſame heart, therefore the more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, <hi>Mali Chriſtianitantò nocentiores quanto interiores mimici,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Tom. 4. <hi>De ſide rerum invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilium,</hi> if that worke be his, the more inward ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies the more hurtfull. Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> deſcanting of the Churches complaint of her bitterneſſe, ſaith ſhe was <hi>amara prius in nece martyrum, amarior poſtea in conflictu haereticorum, amariſſima in moribus domeſticorum:</hi> bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter firſt in the death of her Martyrs, more bitter in ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ages in her concertation with Heretikes, moſt bitter in theſe laſt times in the corrupt manners of them of her owne houſhold.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.26. 1 Iohn 2.19.</note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of perils among falſe brethren, and Saint <hi>John</hi> of ſome, they went out from us,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> but they were not of us, they are not all Iſrael which are of Iſrael, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9 6. And he is a Jew which is one inwardly. Our Saviour mentions ſome that come in ſheeps clothing.<note place="margin">Tertul.</note> 
               <hi>Quae nam ſunt iſt ae pelles ovium, niſi nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Chriſtiani extrinſecus ſuperficies,</hi> they have the name but not the nature of Chriſtians, their habit ſhewes them to be Daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but in heart they are but Daughters of <hi>Babylon,</hi> therefore Chriſt leaves them to a common appellation, not gracing them with his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriating terme, <hi>my.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe whom Chriſt ownes not here he will deny hereafter, and though they be never ſo nigh him, and enjoy all the outward priviledges of the Church, yet <hi>non novi vos,</hi> is their doome: depart from me,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> I know you not.</p>
            <p>So I returne from the Goats to the Sheepe, the Church of Chriſt here compared to a Lily, for as the Lily doth open her ſelfe to receive the bright rayes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of the ſhining Sunne: ſo doth the Church open her heart and affections to admit the heat and ſpirituall vigour of that Sunne of righteouſneſſe; and againe as the Lily ſhuts and cloſeth her ſelfe for her cuſtody and ſafety
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17093:6"/> ſo doth the Church contract and collect herſelfe cloſe together in a holy care and vigilancy to preſerve her ſelfe from the rage and violence of temptations: and further as the Lily is alwayes greene, and changeth not her hew: ſo ought the Chriſtian to be conſtant and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable in holy duties. I will not preſſe the compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon too farre, onely touch the choyce and moſt uſefull parts of the reſemblance.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> obſerves two ſpeciall qualities where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Church doth reſemble the Lily, <hi>propter candorem &amp; odorem,</hi> the whiteneſſe in colour and the ſweetneſſe of ſmell.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whitenes, that is purity, &amp; integrity of conſcience,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.12. Can. 4.7.</note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiles it ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, in this reſpect is the Church ſaid to be all faire, in regard of inward ſincerity, that admits not the ſtaine of blacke and foule hypocriſie, that let all us the children of the Church labour to be like our mother in this divine quality. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency is the badge, the true character of Chriſtians. <hi>Innocentiam profitetur qui Chriſtum profitetur,</hi> as Eraſmus, Chriſtianity is a profeſſion compoſed of innocency. Saint <hi>Benard</hi> obſerves that a Chriſtian of all beaſts is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled to the Lambe, of all birds to the Dove, of all trees to the Vine, of all flowers to the Lily, becauſe the morall predominant quality of them all is innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and this whiteneſſe is the genuine colour of our wedding garment in heaven, and in this life on earth, for the Saints above are deſcribed ſo clad, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.9. And holy <hi>David</hi> ſets them out in the ſame habit, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 24. He that hath cleane hands and a pure heart, and here below our true cogniſance is purity and uprightneſſe of heart, joyned with hands as white as ſnow in <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> for innocency, that no injuſtice may cleave unto our fingers, then ſhall we be like Chriſt our Maſter, in whom was no fault found nor guile in his mouth, and the iſſue ſhall be happy, we ſhall have peace at the laſt.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 37.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17093:7"/>2. Odour or ſweetneſſe, the fragrancy of the Lily is admirable in pleaſing the ſenſes, and with the ſweet ſmell thereof rejoycing the heart, ſo let there be in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Lilies the odour of a good life which may ſmell ſweet in the noſtrils of God and man: of God, that he may teſtifie of us, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> did of <hi>Jacob,</hi> The ſmell of my ſonne is as the ſmell of a field which the Lord hath bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.<note place="margin">Gen. 27.27.</note> Of man, that as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, we may be the ſavour of Chriſt his knowledge in every place, that our name may be <hi>unguentum effuſum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. Cant. 1.3. Luc, 4.14.</note> oyntment powred forth, and as Chriſt his fame went through all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion round about, ſo may the fame of our ſanctity and juſtice be ſpread in thoſe coaſts where we abide, and as the Boxe of Spiknard, wherwith <hi>Mary</hi> anoynted Chriſt, filled the houſe with the odour of the oyntment:<note place="margin">Iohn 12.3</note> ſo the ſavour of our gracious actions may fill the places where we live, then may be the Lily for ſweetneſſe and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grancy.<note place="margin">Zanch. in Hoſ. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> A later Divine notes two other qualities wherin the Church ſhould be like the Lily.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in aboundant fertility; for as he out of <hi>Pliny, Lilio nihil eſt foecundius,</hi> nothing is more fruitfull then the Lily, nor ought to be then a Chriſtian, who ſhould be like thoſe ſheep whereof every one beareth twins, or like the tree of life,<note place="margin">Cant. 4.2. Revel. 22.2.</note> which beareth twelve manner of fruits. Grace admits not of a windy emptineſſe, but the wiſedome that comes from above is full of mercy and good fruits,<note place="margin">Iac, 3.17. Phil. 1.11. Iac. 2.5. 1 Tim. 6.18.</note> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> prayes for the <hi>Philippians,</hi> that they might be filled with the fruits of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; nor of beggerly poverty, but Chriſtians muſt be rich in faith, rich in good workes. Barrenneſſe or fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe not anſwerable to the beſtowed coſt, is accurſed, there is not the ſame expectation of the Lily that growes of it ſelfe in the field, without the art and induſtry of man, and of <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ha in the Garden which is planted, manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and dreſſed with kindly husbandry. Certainely unto whomſoever much is given, of him ſhall be much requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17093:7"/> and they which receive five or two talents, muſt returne a proportionable advantage: where God ſowes a <hi>Gomer,</hi> he will not be content at the harveſt to re<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pe an <hi>Ephah.</hi> Labour we then (my brethren) to abound in the worke of the Lord, to make accounts agreeable to our receits, that ſo we may anſwere the bleſſing, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and expectation of our Maſter: and the fruite of this abundant fruitfulneſſe ſhall be, that an <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rance ſhall be miniſtred unto us abundantly into the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdome of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in a mature and ſeaſonable fructification: as ſoone as the Spring comes, that the Sunne yeelds a nouriſhing heat, the ſweet influences of the Pleiades are looſed, the earth openeth her wombe, and the warm ſhowres and dewes doe diſtill upon it, that it is the time of vegetation; the Lily ſtayes not but immediatly begins to ſhoot and ſhew her ſelfe in fruitfulneſſe: ſo muſt ſpirituall Lilies doe, take the very firſt tender and offer of grace, and readily obey the motions of Gods Spirit: when Gods voyce ſpeakes as in the 27. <hi>Pſa.</hi> ſeeke ye my face, our hearts may eccho to it againe. Thy face Lord will I ſeeke, <hi>Primitiae Deo,</hi> the firſt fruits are fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt for the oblation of the Higheſt, the firſt borne for his ſervice, his ſoule deſires the firſt ripe fruit, the choyceſt trees of Gods Orchard are Palmes and Cedars,<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.11.</note> Palmes bring fruit betimes, and flouriſh abundantly, and Cedars they laſt very long. O take we heed of quenching thoſe bleſſed motions which Gods Spirit breathes into our ſoules, of reſiſting the holy-Ghoſt, of receiving the grace of God in vaine:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.1.</note> depend not too much upon latter raines, and lateward Springs, but when his wind blowes upon our garden,<note place="margin">Cant. 4.16. Pſalm 1.3.</note> let the ſpices thereof flow out: then ſhall we be like the tree-planted by the water ſide, that brings forth his fruit in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yea like the Lily here in the Text.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17093:8"/>
            <p>And now be pleaſed to caſt but your eye upon the Daughters in the comparative part, and then we will view them as they are together, the Lily among the Thornes.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>They are like the Thornes,</head>
               <p n="1">1. For their noxious quality hurtfull to every thing that toucheth them, they will wound and teare not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the garment but the fleſh it ſelfe: I will teare your fleſh with the Thornes of the wilderneſſe:<note place="margin">Iudges 8.7.</note> yea they will putrifie the fleſh where they are hidden: ſo are wicked men full of cruelty, rapine, malignity, yea a ſecret venom they have which empoyſons and corrupts whatſoever they adhere unto. The Prophet deſcribing the generall and deſperate pravity of Prince and people, thus ſeemes to aggravate it; The beſt of them is a bryar, the moſt upright is ſharper then a thorne-hedge:<note place="margin">Micah. 7.4.</note> and the bleſſing promiſed to Iſrael was this: There ſhall be no more a pricking bryar unto the houſe of Iſrael,<note place="margin">Ezek. 28.24.</note> nor any grieving thorne of all that are round about them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For their ſterility and barrenneſſe of fruit, they bring forth nothing immediatly profitable unto man. In the ninth Chapter of <hi>Judges,</hi> there is mention made of the Olives fatneſſe, the Fig-trees ſweetneſſe, the Vines refreſhing and chearing, yet nothing of the thorne and bramble, but unparallelled ambition, pride, diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ends in utter ruine, and deſtruction, yea they are cauſes of barrenneſſe in others, they make the beſt ſoyle and the moſt fruitfull Land barren ſo are evill men unprofitable themſelves, and make others good for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, like the Phariſes who compaſſe Sea and Land to make a Proſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lite,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.15.</note> and when he is made, they make him twofold more the child of hell then themſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.8. Math. 25.</note>Laſtly, for their end, for as of thornes the end is to be burned; ſo everlaſting fire is the iſſue of all ſinfull cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, where they ſhall receive their juſt and deſerved
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17093:8"/> meede in that Lake that burnes with fire and brimſtone forever, where we will leave them, and come to ſpeake of the Church her mixture with them here in this life, as being a Lily among the thornes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>As the Lily among Thornes, ſo is my Love among the Daughters.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> expounds it, <hi>De Eccleſia Gentium quae velè medio remedio infidelium &amp; non credentium quaſi ex spinis emerſerit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hier. in Cant.</note> God doth ſelect and picke out his Church of the Gentiles from among unbeleevers, as a Lily out of a great heape of thornes, ſo in the Prophet, <hi>I found Iſrael like grapes in the wilderneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſeah, 9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>where no man expected them,</hi> yea God doth finde us like Lilyes among thornes, but even when we are very thornes as hurtfull, as unfruitfull, as fit for the fire as they, till God of thornes make us Lilyes, therefore let us glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the riches of his grace, and ſet forrh the prayſe of him who hath changed our diſpoſition, made us inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, pleaſing to himſelfe, profitable to others, and ſhall be one day tranſplanted into his Celeſtiall Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> underſtands it of the mixture of good and bad in the viſible Church,<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſ. <hi>99.</hi>
                  </note> Lily and Thornes promiſcuouſly growing together, ſo that the Church is like <hi>Rebeccahs</hi> wombe, two ſeverall Nations are in it, like <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, that hath cleane and uncleane beaſts in it, like Saint <hi>Peters</hi> net, which gathered fiſh and rubbiſh, like the <hi>Samaritans</hi> Inne entertaines all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of gueſts: wheate and chaffe in one floore, meale and branne in one lumpe: and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, in a great houſe there are not onely veſſels of gold and ſilver, but of wood and ſtone, ſome to honour, and ſome to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Tria ſunt loca,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Ber. Sent.</hi>
                  </note> there be three places, heaven, hell, and earth, &amp; each of theſe hath his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17093:9"/> ſeverall Inhabitants: Heaven hath none but good, hell none but bad, the earth hath good and bad mixed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Saint <hi>Austin</hi> ſeemes to apply it briefely, thus.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Aug. loc. cit.</note>1. <hi>Quomodo conſolaris?</hi> how doſt thou comfort thy Church, (O Lord) againſt the multitude of ungodly men? ſhe may ſeeme to deſpaire when ſhe ſees ſuch thickets of thornes, as if all was turned to a wilderneſſe, yet there is hope for her in this, <hi>ſunt grana inter paleam, est Lilium inter spinas,</hi> There be ſome graines of corne amongſt the great heapes of chaffe, and a Lily among the multitude of thornes. Thus God cheares up <hi>Elijah</hi> in his grievous complaint, I have left me ſeven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand that have not bowed the knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet tells the people,<note place="margin">1 Kings 19.18. Revel 2.4.</note> there is a remnant, and there be a few names in <hi>Sardis, Mathew</hi> and <hi>Zachey</hi> among the Publicanes, the Centurion among the Souldiers, <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> among the harlots. Therefore though we doe <hi>gemere</hi> as he ſaith, mourne that the wayes of <hi>Sion</hi> want paſſengers, yet let us not mourne as <hi>Rachel</hi> for her children, refuſing to be comforted becauſe they were not, nor ſorrow as they that are without hope. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe many ſhall come from the Eaſt and from the Weſt, and ſit downe with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> in that bleſſed Kingdome above, though we be not privy to the places they have there, nor to their going thither, the Church herſelfe ſaith, in admiration of her encreaſed number, who hath begotten me theſe, ſeeing I have loſt my children,<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.21.</note> and am deſolate, a captive and remooving to and fro? and who hath brought up theſe? behold I was left alone, theſe where had they beene? And take we heed of over ſullen cenſures, leaſt we condemne the generation of Gods children, and take them for thornes which were Lilies,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
                  <hi>De nullo pronuntiandum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Quomodo confor<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as?</hi> How doſt thou ſtrengthen us againſt the temptations of Satan and the ſeductions
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17093:9"/> of wicked men? when thou telleſt us thy Church is and continueth a Lily though amongſt never ſo many thorns, ſhe is (as I have already ſaid) in a ſpeciall manner in Chriſt his care and cuſtody, in his hands, and none ſhall be able to plucke her thence, built upon a rocke, and remaines like mount <hi>Sion</hi> immoveable.<note place="margin">Pſal. 125.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Quomodo terres?</hi> How doſt thou affright us with the conſideration of our dangerous and militant condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here on earth, that we are beſet with thornes, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> caſe, bryars and thornes are with us,<note place="margin">Ezekiel, 2.6.</note> and we dwell among Scorpions, and as God left the <hi>Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> to be pricks in the eyes, and thornes in the ſides of Iſrael to teach them warre, <hi>Judges</hi> 3.2. So hath he left us enemies to traine us up in our military profeſſion of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That which is oppoſite to the ſcope of his expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of the Text it ſelfe, is to perſwade us, <hi>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re malos,</hi> to be content to beare with and forbeare them that be evill, for God himſelfe hath ſaid, that the tares ſhall not onely be, but grow among the wheat, untill the Harveſt, and the bad ſhall be amongſt the good in the ſame net,<note place="margin">Math. 13.30. <hi>Aug. tom.</hi> 4. <hi>de Catech.</hi> 12. <hi>rud.</hi>
                  </note> untill they be drawne to ſhoare at the end of the world, even, he <hi>quem nihil frurorum latet,</hi> who knoweth right well what they are, and what they will be, ſuffereth them not onely to enjoy being, but well being, all manner of outward bleſſings, cauſeth his Sun to ſhine, and his raine to raine upon them, yea Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the dayes of his fleſh endured, even the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of ſinners, ſo that all thoſe furious ſpirits, that ſeeke an immediate and uttereradication of the thorns, and if it lay in their power, would command fire from heaven to conſume them, doe not imitate theſe bleſſed examples, ſhow a great deale of non-proficiency in Chriſtianity, as Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. decerpt. ſen.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui ideo neminem vult pati hominum quia ut arbitratur multum proficit, per hoc <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pſum quod alios non tolerat, oſtendit quod potius non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit,</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17093:10"/> a great want of patience, yea of Chriſtian charity, which ſtill hopes the beſt, judgeth nothing till the time come, and hath alwayes a mantle ready to cover the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of others,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.14.</note> yea, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to beare them up as a crouch doth a body that is lame, or a beame a houſe, that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining, whereas theſe are ready to diſcover the naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of others, and even to thruſt their fingers into their wounds to make them greater; and ſo in an unjuſt unchriſtian way, ſeparate themſelves, and while they relinquiſh the flock for the Goates ſake, crept in amongſt them, they leave the ſheepe expoſed to the rage of the wolfe, whereas they ought to beare with the Goates for the ſheeps ſake,<note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>48.</hi> Vicentio.</note> 
                  <hi>Non enim propter malos boni deſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendi, ſed propter bonos mali tolerandi,</hi> The good are not to be forſaken by reaſon of thoſe amongſt them; which are evill, but the evill are to be tolerated in regard of thoſe amongſt them which are good, yea in forſaking them that,<note place="margin">Aug. tom. <hi>6.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Fauſtum, man. l. <hi>13.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> be good, they relinquiſh Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>cum iſti re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquuntur iſte relin quitur,</hi> who accounts himſelfe relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, when they are relinquiſhed which he accounts of: that queſtion of S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> is very fit for every one of them who precipitate Gods judgement.<note place="margin">Tom. <hi>9</hi> Hom. de <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vib. c. <hi>10.</hi> li. c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hanc tune Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus eradicans zizania?</hi> art thou the Angell which muſt pluck up the tares? and in the ſame Homily, <hi>Homo carne ſeptus carnem portans, aut fortè caro totus, id eſt, caro corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, carnalis animo, audes uſurpate officium alienum, quod nec in meſſe erit tuum?</hi> Dares thou being perhaps carnall, at leaſt clothed with fleſh, and a man of like paſſions with others, uſurpe that office which ſhall never belong unto thee but to the Angels, and not be theirs, till the end of the world? and whereas thou ſhouldeſt ſupplicate for the further manuring and longer growth of the tree, doſt thou antevert a commiſſion to cut it downe, that it may comber the ground no longer? rather <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe thou ſay and deſire, as he, deſtroy it not, there is a bleſſing in it, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 65.8. I will cloſe this point wirh that of Saint
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17093:10"/> 
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> worthy to be written in letters of gold, <hi>Etſi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur in Eccleſiaeſſe zizania, non tamen impediri debet, aut fides aut charitas noſtra,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cyp. ep. l. <hi>3.</hi> ep <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ut quoniam zizania eſſe i<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Eccleſia cernimus, ipſi de Eccleſia recedamus. Nobis modò laboran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ut frumentum eſſe poſſumus, ut cum caeperit frumentum Dominicis horreis condi fructum pro opere noſtro, &amp; labore capiamus.</hi> The being of tares in the field, the Church ought not to be a hindrance to our faith or charity, nor is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſe of our ſeparation from the Church, we ſhould rather labour to be good corne our ſelves, that when the Harveſt comes we may be gathered into Gods Barne, &amp; there receive the fruit of our faith and obedience or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as he goes on, There be in a great houſe veſſels of wood and earth, made for inferiour uſes, and others of gold and ſilver made for honourable ſervices: thus it is in Gods great houſe, the Church, we muſt labour to be veſſels of honour, fit for our Maſters uſe, and leave thoſe of baſer metall to his diſpoſall, who will at his own time breake them in pieces like a Potters veſſell.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Junius</hi> thinks it ſpoken of the excellency &amp; digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church in compariſon of other Congregations,<note place="margin">Iun. in loc.</note> and of ſuch as are not truly hers, though mixed with hers. <hi>Tantum ſuperat Eccleſia coeteros omnes caetus quantum Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium ſpinas.</hi> The Church doth as far excell all other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations in worth, as the Lily doth thorns. Our Saviour ſpeaks of the Lily, that even <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his Royalty was not arrayed like one of them,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.29.</note> if <hi>Solomon</hi> the moſt glorious Prince, in the height of his glory attained not to the lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre of the Lily: what a low ranke muſt the burre, bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, a thorne be of, to the ſpirituall Lily? what is <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaven</hi> to <hi>Bethel,</hi> the houſe of <hi>Ammon</hi> to the houſe of God? the Tents of <hi>Sedar</hi> to the Tabernacle of Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? <hi>Abana</hi> and <hi>Pharpar,</hi> the puddle waters of <hi>Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> to the cleare waters of Iſrael, the wells of ſalvation? glorious things are ſpoken of the City, the Church of God, as glorious ſhe is as the Sunne when he goes forth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17093:11"/> in his might, <hi>Judges</hi> 5.31. nay, more glorious then the other Sunne, for ſhe is clothed with the Sunne of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Revel. 12.11,</note> and the Moone under her feet. They ſay the Pope is greater then any Prince of the earth, by ſo many degrees as the Sunne is greater then the earth; let Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites ſay what they will, we may truly lay the compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the true Church of Chriſt doth infinitely excell that Antichriſtian Synagogue of Satan, and all prophane Congregations, though they aſſume to themſelves never ſo many vaine titles of honour, as <hi>Sancta Eccleſia Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholica Romana,</hi> and ſo forth, and <hi>Muſſelmanni,</hi> as the Turkes title themſelves true beleevers, yet are they all thornes to the pure Lily, the Church. If it be referred to the Daughrers ſuch as I have mentioned, that live within the pale of the viſible Church, yet are not the peculiar Spouſe of Chriſt. The truly Chriſtian ſoule as farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds them, as the Lily doth the thornes; what compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon is there betwixt the gold and the droſſe? the wine and the lees? the faithfull Spouſe of Chriſt, and the filthy harlot of the Devill? ſurely one little ſpot of ground <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhen</hi> that hath light in it, is worth all Aegypt full of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, groſſe and palpable. Learne we highly to eſteeme theſe Lilies, and to prize theſe choyce jewels, and in whomſoever we ſee true grace, ſanctity and juſtice, which two are the candour and odour of the Lily, to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue them, though they be beſet with never ſo many thornes of infirmities or adverſities, let us account of them as they are, indeed the heires of heaven, the nobles of the world, for <hi>Generoſa Chriſti feſta, nobilitat viros cui quiſquis ſervit ille vere eſt nobilis,</hi> and the pledges of our peace, it may be the fire had beene before this time ſent into the thornes, but that there are ſome Lilies amongſt them to be preſerved, and for their ſakes God doth ſpare the thornes ſo long.</p>
               <p>Our later Divines have obſerved many other reaſons and reſpects why the Church may be ſaid to be a Lily
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17093:11"/> among the thornes: I will onely rub ſome few of their eares of corne, and leave the harveſt to ſome other choyce worke-man his gathering. <hi>A Lily among thornes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. In regard of the multitude of afflictions ſhe ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in this life, for the Church hath ever beene like <hi>Abrahams</hi> Ram held in a thicket of adverſity, <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> is <hi>Crutianus,</hi> as <hi>Luther</hi> was wont to ſay, a man of croſſes. The ſervant is not above his maſter, God had but one only Son, and he was <hi>ſine peccato,</hi> yet not <hi>ſine ſtagello.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. in Pſa.</hi> 31. Luc. 9 23. <hi>Beza.</hi>
                  </note> Therefore let us take up our Croſſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a day by day, <hi>ut dies diem ſequitur, ita crux crucem accipiat</hi> every day we muſt expect ſufficient travell, and with patience let us poſſeſſe our ſoules for it, reſolve that through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tribulation and afflict ons, we muſt enter into Gods Kingdome, if we will have Chriſt, his Crowne of glory,<note place="margin">Acts, 14 22.</note> we muſt be content to weare a crowne of thornes. For the Church is a Lily among thornes.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In regard of the manifold impediments ſhe hath to hinder her ſpirituall growth, namely,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Satan is a blacke thorne in his temptations, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes pricking and wounding the children of God, yea biting at the very root of the Lily, like the worme at the root of <hi>Jonahs</hi> Gourd, and the Lily would as ſoone wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as that Gourd did, was there not a ſoveraigne power from above to preſerve it, pray we then unto God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke Satan in all his aſſaults, that our Lily may flouriſh in deſpight of him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, naturall corruption which God hath left to be pricks in our eyes, and thornes in our ſides. Sa<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt <hi>Paul,</hi> that choyce veſſell of grace complaines of them, <hi>Rom</hi> 7. I cary about me a body of ſinne and death, he calls it by the very terme in my Text, the thorne in the fleſh, the meſſenger of Satan to buffet me, take we his courſe even to ſolicite God by frequent prayer,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.7.</note> till we have the ſame anſwer which he obtained, my grace ſhall be ſufficient for thee, and begge of him who comes with healing in his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17093:12"/> wings to heale our nature, that it may not be ſo fruitfull in bringing forth theſe pricking thorns. S. <hi>Bernard</hi> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larizeth theſe to be <hi>Amores ſeculares immoderate,</hi> earthly deſires, &amp; worldly cogitations, which brings a barrennes of goodnes to the ſoule,<note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> and choak the ſeed of the word. <hi>O munde, munde,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Austin, Fallax &amp; proditor,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure world, a traitor to us and a deceiver of us. It glues our wings, that we cannot ſoare upwards, and as he that hath a thorne in his foot is utterly unfit for travell, ſo he that hath theſe thorns of worldly cares ſtick in his ſoule, is unmeet for his journey to heaven. Let us therfore pluck out this thorne, and if riches encreaſe, ſet not our heart upon them.<note place="margin">Pſal. 62.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, the perverſe and ſinfull converſation of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, which are thornes in our way to heaven, the ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> ſhall be as thornes thruſt away,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.67.</note> becauſe they cannot be taken with hands, but the man that ſhall touch them muſt be fenced with Iron,<note place="margin">Cant. 1.6.</note> and the ſtaffe of a Speare. The Church complaines that her mothers ſons made her the keeper of the Vineyards, but her owne Vineyard ſhe kept not, and hath not every member of the Church cauſe to complaine with <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm 119.61. <hi>Bern. in Cant. Ser.</hi> 48.</note> the bands of wicked men have robbed me? Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> is ſeaſonable for a cloſe of this point, <hi>Si Lilium eſt inter spinas videat una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſque anima quam vigilem ſolicit ámque eſſe oporteat ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cuſtodia ſui, ſepta undique ſpinis hinc inde aculeos inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus,</hi> The Church is like a Lily beſet round about with thornes, that ſeeke to wound and teare her, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let every ſoule be watchfull and carefull for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of it ſelfe, that neither the thorne within doe impoiſon her, nor thoſe other without doe pierce her to hinder her growth in grace here, or to deprive her of glory hereafter.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In regard of the ſmall number of thoſe that are the true members of the Church, in compariſon of forreine Congregations without, and falſe brethren within, one
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17093:12"/> Lily many thornes. <hi>Plures mali,</hi> they which are evill,<note place="margin">Byas.</note> are the greateſt number. There is much mold whereof earthen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels are made, but little duſt that gold commeth of,<note place="margin">2 Eſdras 8.</note> many trees are planted, but few like that good tree bring forth fruit in their ſeaſon: much ſeed is ſowne, but three parts thereof miſcary, Saint <hi>Auguſtin</hi> gives a good rule,<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſ. <hi>39.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Noli nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merare ſed appende, ſtateram affer aequam non doloſam,</hi> Doe not take them by number, but conſider well of them, weigh them in the ballance of the Sanctuary, or elſe thou miſtakeſt, then afterwards, <hi>Noli imitari,</hi> Doe not imitate them that be the moſt, or in words of holy writ, Thou ſhalt not follow a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to doe evill; the reaſon is given by one,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſt turba ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per argumentum peſſimi,</hi> the worſe goe by heapes and troopes, the leaſt are oftentimes ſolitary, of twenty Kings of Iſrael, not one good that cleave to the Lord with all his heart, of ſixe hundred thouſand Iſraelites, but two came into the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> It was a remarkeable folly and puniſhment of <hi>Radbodus</hi> King of <hi>Friſia,</hi> who asking whether there were moſt in heaven or hell, and was anſwered, that in hell was the greateſt number, withdrew himſelfe from holy baptiſme, and profeſſed plainely that he would goe to hell, where the moſt company was, but he injoyed his madnes and contempt of Gods Ordinance but a ſhort ſpace, for the third day after, he dyed ſuddenly. It is better to be with <hi>Noah</hi> &amp; his ſmall fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Arke, then with the whole world to be drowned in the deluge, to be planted in Gods garden with the Lily, then to be throwne into the fire with a whole wildernes of thorns.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Laſtly, the Church is as the Lily among thornes in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of her unity and their diviſions and diſtractions, being torne in more pieces then the Prophet <hi>Ahjiahs</hi> garment was, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12. for that was onely into twelve, but theſe are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, parted into as many ſeverall conventicles are there be men of deepely corrupt minds, who doe <hi>partes facere,</hi> as Saint <hi>Augustin</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and gather diſciples unto themſelves,<note place="margin">Aug. de unitate Eccleſiae. c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quis poſſit ſingulas quaſi haereſes enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re gentium ſingalarem?</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> who is able to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17093:13"/> reckon up all the hereſies of every ſeverall Nation,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de unitate Eccleſiae, c.</hi> 3. Daniel, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> yea the ſeverall Sects that are in one Nation, theſe hold not the head Chriſt, and are as thoſe beaſts of <hi>Daniel,</hi> diverſe one from another, yet all againſt the Church, as the enemies to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and folded together to doe more miſchiefe, as the thorns are,<note place="margin">Nahum. 1.10.</note> they have <hi>unitatem contra unitatem,</hi> as S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, I am ſure <hi>contra veritatem,</hi> a unity againſt truth, for our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour tells us not onely of many falſe Prophets, but of falſe Chriſts. But there is but one true Chriſt the head, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers are the ſeverall members of his myſticall body, united by faith to him their head, and in Chriſtian charity one to another; and though there be threeſcore Queenes and foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Concubines, and Virgins without number, yet is Chriſt his Spouſe <hi>una &amp; unica,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 6.9.</note> one and the onely one of her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, that there is but one body, one ſpirit, one hope of their ſpirituall calling, one Lord, one faith, one baptiſme, one God and Father, of all who is above all, our through all,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.4, 5. Iohn, 17.</note> and in all his children, therefore they ought all to be one, as our Saviour prayed for them five times in one Chapter, the very thornes will leſſon us in this duty; ſhall they be folded together to doe hurt, and ſhall not the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies hold together to preſerve one another? It is unity will make our colour more candid, out odour more fragrant, and fruitfulneſſe,<note place="margin">Aug. ep. <hi>15.</hi> Hieronymo.</note> more ſeaſonable and aboundant. For <hi>omnis pulchritudinis forma unitas,</hi> unity is the forme of beauty and uniformity is the forme of unity, where there is <hi>cor unum,</hi> and <hi>viauna,</hi> one heart and one way, the carriage of things will be proſper<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, the end comfortable. I will cloſe then with that prayer of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 3.15.</note> Now the Lord of peace himſelfe give us peace us alwayes, by all meanes, and that for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, the Prince of peace, who dearely bought our peace by his precious blood, to whom with the Father and the holy-Ghoſt, be given all glory, dominion, might, majeſty, and thankeſgiving from this time forth and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
